<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Lucas' Refuge</title><link href="http://x8lucas8x.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://x8lucas8x.com/feeds/tags/consumer-driven-contracts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://x8lucas8x.com/</id><updated>2015-10-18T20:40:00-03:00</updated><entry><title>On Integration Testing and Microservices</title><link href="http://x8lucas8x.com/on-integration-testing-and-microservices.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-18T20:40:00-03:00</updated><author><name>x8lucas8x</name></author><id>tag:x8lucas8x.com,2015-10-18:on-integration-testing-and-microservices.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;To begin with, higher level (e.g. end-to-end, integration) testing lacks several
benefits of unit testing, many of which we have come to value as an industry. On
the other hand, not all bugs are apparent at an unit level. They could also
happen on the wiring between components or even at those off-the-shelf solutions
you employed to speed up your development. Yet you often heard the agile community
endorsing unit tests as the backbone of a solid testing strategy. People like
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mikewcohn"&gt;@mikewcohn&lt;/a&gt;, who established the initial model of the &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TestPyramid.html"&gt;testing pyramid&lt;/a&gt;, often
advocate that the ratio of a particular kind of test, in your test suite, should
be inversely proportional to the degree of granularity of the tested scope.
Principle that helps a solid test suite to be built in the most cost-effective way.
And beware, since going in the opposite direction may result in an instance of the
&lt;a href="http://watirmelon.com/2012/01/31/introducing-the-software-testing-ice-cream-cone/"&gt;ice cream cone&lt;/a&gt; anti pattern. So, even though you certainly could find several
definitions for the properties of good unit tests out there, those roughly translate&amp;nbsp;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isolated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Idempotent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is easy to explain, as long-running tests are the easiest way to make
programmers develop the bad habit of avoid running tests frequently. And, if that
happens, what is the point anyway? Automated since the intention is to facilitate
adoption, not making people do repetitive work. Isolated because they should not
overlap, otherwise you would have more places to look for when something fails.
Informative, because the context of the failure should be explicit. Yep, you probably
do not want people to analyse your test&amp;#8217;s source so that they can understand what
went wrong. Finally, idempotency implies that they should behave the same, no matter
which order or how many times they were run. Believe me, tests that randomly fail
are a recipe for madness. They are worse than no tests at all, as they undermine
developers&amp;#8217; trust in their test&amp;nbsp;suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how does those properties apply to higher level (e.g. end-to-end, integration)
testing. First, they are not as fast as unit tests. Especially if you are testing
two &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/microservices.html"&gt;microservices&lt;/a&gt;, process that would involve exchanging some packets over the
network (latency sucks :/). They are not idempotent too, as there are many ways
they could go wrong. Units that rely in global state (e.g. singleton pattern)
can also suffer from that, but a proper use of dependency injection can fix
the problem. As for lost packets, network partition, good luck with it. Informative,
well, you know something in between a set of components/services is not working well.
Isolated? Nope, even though you can be cautious enough to avoid chatty
components/services, one bug in one of them and you would suddenly find yourself in
a situation in which every code path along the way fail. But hey, they could be&amp;nbsp;automated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you find my point of view a bit extreme? Then try &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jbrains"&gt;@jbrains&lt;/a&gt; amazing talk titled
&lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/80533536"&gt;Integrated Tests Are A Scam&lt;/a&gt;. He goes even further by showing how the promises of high
level testing lures developers into writing more tests of the same kind that, at the end,
would provide very few coverage. Due to the combinatorial explosion of required tests,
needed for the continuously increasing code paths. Instead, he advocates that we should
spend our time with worthwhile tests. By worthwhile he means tests that help assessing
the quality of our architecture, allowing us to improve its design in the long run.
Seriously, if you want to laugh a bit with integrated tests&amp;#8217; infamous positive feedback
loop of negative emotions, watch it. Additionally, a written equivalent of it is
available at &lt;a href="http://www.jbrains.ca/permalink/integrated-tests-are-a-scam-part-1"&gt;Integrated Tests are a Scam: Part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.jbrains.ca/permalink/part-2-some-hidden-costs-of-integration-tests"&gt;Part 2: Some Hidden Costs of Integration Tests&lt;/a&gt;, he also discusses about an important
side-effect of slow tests, they destroy developers&amp;#8217; productivity. Waiting for a few seconds
is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, but it is not rare to find tests suites that take ten minutes or more. Unfortunately,
one cannot simply return to him/her peak performance right after such a long interruption.
In &lt;a href="http://www.jbrains.ca/permalink/part-3-the-risks-associated-with-lengthy-tests"&gt;Part 3: The risks associated with lengthy tests&lt;/a&gt;, the focus changes to the insidious
consequences of frequent false alerts, given the lack of isolation when things fail. And
with less trust in the test suite, a fear of change starts to evolve among developers.
Individuals that tend to justify their behaviour by mentioning an old engineering saying
&amp;#8220;Well, if it works, why change it?&amp;#8221;. Rationale that will ultimately lead to an architectural
stagnation and to high interest rates in the form of &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TechnicalDebt.html"&gt;technical debt&lt;/a&gt;. Quite the contrary to
what you expected when you got bought into the practice of &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/SelfTestingCode.html"&gt;self testing code&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But do not get him wrong, his disregard for integration testing limits itself to cases
in which they are used for assessing basic correctness. Role that is better suited to
unit tests, in the first place. In &lt;a href="http://www.jbrains.ca/permalink/using-integration-tests-mindfully-a-case-study"&gt;Using integration tests mindfully: a case study&lt;/a&gt;, for
instance, he does see a value of employing integration tests for identifying system-level
issues like broken database schema, mistaken cache integration, and more complex problems.
That is, using integration tests to check the presence of a expected feature, is perfectly&amp;nbsp;fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, in &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/80533536"&gt;Integrated Tests Are A Scam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jbrains"&gt;@jbrains&lt;/a&gt; proposes an alternative for testing the
interaction between components without resorting to integration testing. He suggests
combining collaboration and contract tests. Collaboration tests are a well known practice,
often named as &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TestDouble.html"&gt;test doubles&lt;/a&gt;. More specifically, stubs are the the kind of doubles we
are interested in. Stubs tend to mimic others&amp;#8217; interfaces, but instead of doing real work,
they return pre-computed results. Behaviour that is really useful when non-deterministic
or slow operations (e.g. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IO&lt;/span&gt;) are at stake, as we can employ fast and predictable unit-like
tests to achieve a similar end. As for contract tests, they check the format of an
component/service response, not its data. So, in the case of &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/microservices.html"&gt;microservices&lt;/a&gt;, you would
be testing if the outcome of a particular call has the fields you expected and if so,
whether they comply with your use cases. Similarly, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/martinfowler"&gt;@martinfowler&lt;/a&gt; also see the combination
of stubs and contract tests as a good way to tackle the slowness and unreliability of
integration tests, as stated in &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/IntegrationContractTest.html"&gt;integration contract test&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One challenge though is that testing against a double does not guarantee that the external
component/service is being accurately represented. And even if so, future changes would
require the double to be updated accordingly. One alternative to streamline the updates of
stubs would be what &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/martinfowler"&gt;@martinfowler&lt;/a&gt; calls &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/SelfInitializingFake.html"&gt;self initialising fakes&lt;/a&gt;. Similarly, contract
testing also suffers from the same synchronisation burden, however &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/SelfInitializingFake.html"&gt;self initialising fakes&lt;/a&gt;
cannot help contract tests in the same manner. Additionally, there is also the possibility of
contracts and stubs getting out of sync. Problem that could be mitigated by a shared metadata
file or data structure that specifies available calls and what should be received in response,
so that you do not have to concern yourself with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reduce the odds of getting out of sync, therefore breaking your test cases, or even
worse, being misled by passing tests that should have failed, it is recommended to adopt
a consumer-driven contract approach. In &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/consumerDrivenContracts.html"&gt;Consumer-Driven Contracts: A Service Evolution
Pattern&lt;/a&gt;, the concept is explained in a relatively implementation agnostic fashion. In a
nutshell, consumer-driven contracts are a means of applying &amp;#8220;just enough&amp;#8221; validation, as
proposed by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robustness_principle"&gt;John Postel&amp;#8217;s Law&lt;/a&gt;, which puts the responsibility to specify what the service
provider must comply on the clients. The service provider must then check the union of
its consumers&amp;#8217; expectations, in order to verify that there were no regressions. Additionally,
that approach has some notable design advantages. First, it facilitates evolving your
interface, as you wouldn&amp;#8217;t have to rely on schema extension points for adding new fields
to your messages. Second, since what is consumed is explicitly stated, deprecating a field
that nobody is using is way&amp;nbsp;easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the usefulness of mixing stubs and consumer-driven contract tests have led
to the development of frameworks such as &lt;a href="https://github.com/realestate-com-au/pact"&gt;Pact&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://thoughtworks.github.io/pacto/"&gt;Pacto&lt;/a&gt;, both written in Ruby. More
importantly, they facilitate your stubs and contract tests to be in sync. Personally, I
think that frameworks like that are a really promising way for guaranteeing compatibility
among services&amp;#8217; interfaces, while maintaining many of the unit testing properties. So, next
time you get yourself considering to test some &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/microservices.html"&gt;microservices&lt;/a&gt; with integration testing,
think twice. If you just want to check compatibility among services&amp;#8217; interfaces, invest in
stubs and consumer-driven contract testing&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="microservices"></category><category term="integration testing"></category><category term="test doubles"></category><category term="consumer-driven contracts"></category><category term="soa"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry></feed>